Curriculum vitae of Md. Suman Miah

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Md. Suman Miah

Present/Mailing Address: Holding No: 677/4, Jahabox Lane, Gabtola, Moghbazar,

Ramna Model, Dhaka-1217, Bangladesh; Contact no: +8801750497710

Permanent Address: House: 1524, Ward: 10, Vill- Bakhtiarpur, P.O- Keranirhat,

P.S- Rangpur Sadar, District- Rangpur, Bangladesh

Email: suman.rubd@yahoo.com

Web: https://www.linkedin.com/in/sumangeo/

Skype: Suman.rbd; Sex: Male; Date of birth: 11 December, 1989; Nationality: Bangladeshi,

Driving License: RJ0031630CL0004; NID: 8235908194; TIN: 815108320273; Passport: A00653489;

SUMMARY

I am a dedicated and self-motivated Hydrology monitoring & evaluation practitioner in the humanitarian and development sector. Experienced in climate change impact/vulnerability/risk assessment; adaptation and resilience research in water, sanitation, and climate change in South Asia. By training, I am a hydrogeologist while I have advanced training in governance, M&E, water resources, and environmental management. I am actively pursuing a challenging key position as a Hydrology Lead in development sector to take my career to the next level and expand my experience. My career interest is to contribute to sustainable global development especially in Bangladesh and other South Asian countries.

EDUCATION

- 1. August 2012 October 2014: Master of Science (MS) in Geology and Mining, University of Rajshahi, Bangladesh; Major Courses: Water Management and Irrigation, Groundwater Basin Modeling, Groundwater Pollution, Geo-Hazards and Disaster Management, Waste Management and Environmental Geochemistry.
- April 2008 July 2012: Bachelor of Science (BSc) in Geology and Mining, University of Rajshahi, Bangladesh. Major Courses: Geological Mapping, Geomechanics, Sedimentology, Stratigraphy, Geo tectonic, Hydrogeology, Geophysics, Remote Sensing and GIS, Petroleum Geology, Geotechnical Engineering,
- 3. August 2005 May 2007: Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC); Science, Rangpur Govt. College, Rangpur, Bangladesh.
- 4. January 2003 April 2005: Secondary School Certificate (SSC); Science, Bir Uttam Shaheed Samad High School, Rangpur Cantonment, Rangpur, Bangladesh.

TRAINING AND SHORT COURSES

- 1. September 2019: Completed 2 weeks short course on "Multilevel Water Governance", in The Hague Academy for Local Governance, The Hague, Netherlands, funded by OKP Scholarship, Netherlands.
- 2. February 2021 March 2021: Accomplished 2 weeks training course on "Toilet Technoogies, Faecal Sludge and Water Management in Rural Areas" organised by Centre for Science and Environment (CSE), New Delhi, India.
- 3. October 2019 December 2019: Undertook 2 months short course on International Water Law and the Law of Transboundary Aquifers (4 ECTS credits) by Geneva Water Hub in collaboration with DiploFoundation and University of Geneva, Switzerland. Scholarship funded by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation.
- 4. August 2016: Succeeded 3 days training on "Integrated Water Resource Management (IWRM)" organised by DASCOH Foundation, Swiss Red Cross and Rural Development Academy, Bogura, Bangladesh. Topics covered: IWRM way forward, Water Resource Management tools and technology, Case Study.
- 5. June 2015: Completed 3 days training on Conflict Sensitive Program Management (CSPM), organised by Swiss Red Cross and DASCOH Foundation, Bangladesh. Topics covered: Conflict issue management, Crisis Management, development concept, monitoring process and technique.
- 6. March 2021: Attained 3 days training on "Asia Pacific Virtual Winter School 2021 for Young and Emerging Evaluators (YEEs)" in Asia Pacific region organized by Asia Pacific Evaluation Association (APEA) in partnership with EvalYouth Asia (EYA), Sri Lanka Evaluation Association (SLEvA), Evaluation Community of India (ECOI), EvalYouth Sri Lanka, EvalYouth India, EvalYouth Afghanistan, EvalYouth Pakistan and the Center for Evaluation at University of Sri Jayewardenepura.
- 7. June 2017: Achieved 5 days training on "Measuring Resilience" organised by Swiss Red Cross, Bangladesh Red Crescent and Banyaneer. Topics covered: Disaster Management, Climate Resilience Radar, and Data Collection Method by apps and online and Monitoring and evaluation (M&E).
- 8. March 2018: Completed 2 days training on "Report Writing" organised by DASCOH Foundation, Bangladesh. Topics covered: Important aspects of report writing, type, preparation, process, style, practice.
- 9. October 2020: Completed 1 week training on International Project Management based on PRINCE2 (PRojects IN Controlled Environments), by Global Skills Development Agency, registered under AXELOS Limited. I have acclereted myself in - Project Management Framework and Processes, develop a management plan, Leadership and Communications, Critical Path Analysis & Best Practice Project Planning, Risk & Issue Management, Project Reporting, Gantt chart, Project Quality Management.
- 10. October 2020 November 2020: Awarded 1 month training on "Online Meetings and Conferences: How to Run Effective and Secure Events" by Diplo Foundation, financial supported by the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs of Switzerland.

- 11. September 2014 December 2014: Earned 3 months training on Content Management System by Bangladesh High-tech Park Authority. Skill covered: HTML, CSS, PHP, Wordpress installation, content develop and manage.
- 12. January 2015 June 2015: Completed 6 months course on "Database Programming Certificate in Skill Standard Basic Course Examination" by Bangladesh Technical Education Board, Dhaka; Secured Grade: A+.
- 13. April 2020: Completed 3 days training on MEAL DPro: Monitoring, Evaluation, Accountability and Learning, by Humanitarian Leadership Academy, Humanitum and Catholic Relief Services (CRS). I've learned the topics: Humanitarian Essentials, Accountability, Programmatic Support, Programme design, Monitoring and evaluation, Quality and governance, Fundraising and donor management, Management Essentials, Project management.
- 14. March 2020: Completed short training on Monitoring, Evaluation, Accountability and Learning (MEAL) in Emergencies, by Save the Children. Topics covered: Understanding of the key principles of Monitoring, Evaluation, Accountability and Learning (MEAL) in Emergency Contexts.

WORK EXPERIENCE

- 1. April 2021 Recent as Individual Local Consultant (Data Processor) in 'Mouza and Plot based National Digital Landzoing Project' of Ministry of Land, Bangladesh. This project is funded by Government of Bangladesh (GoB). I am working closely under the supervision of Monitoring and Evaluation specialist to support and process the surveyed field data for land use plan and efficient land management by dividing the land into plots for agriculture, housing, commercial, tourism and industrial development according to the quality of the land; Provide training on land use and conduct public awareness campaigns; Thus, I am contributing to efficient system in land administration and management which specifically mentioned in the implementation of SDG's Goal-9, 11, 15 and Delta Plan 2100. I am assisting in formulation of existing land use plan including collection of remote sensing images of a particular area on mouza map sheets, scanned maps and digitized copies, projection and georeferencing and preparation of digitized land zoning maps based on mouzas and plots. Also, organize workshops, publicity campaigns to make the local people and stakeholders aware to help in resolving conflicts in land use of the parties concerned and reduce all forms of inequality at the regional and local levels.
- 2. June 2015 April 2021 as 'Monitoring and ICT Officer' in DASCOH Foundation in 'Integrated Water Resources Management Project (IWRM)' project (Both in phase 1 & 2) jointly implemented by the Swiss Red Cross, financed by Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation SDC. Within my job responsibilities, I have developed 26 methodologies, tools, formats for ground water monitoring and project monitoring purposes, and guided staff for efficient use. Also, I have designed, conducted, and analyzed baseline, midline, and endline surveys for the annual internal evaluations. Hence, I've collected and preserved data in periodic output and outcome-focused monitoring databases and documented it with reports of water resources, ongoing activities, feedbacks, and outcomes of the project regularly. I established the project's MIS system that supported institutionalizing the water quality monitoring system at local government institutions. Prepared three annual and three half-yearly outcome-focused operational reports. I designed and conducted 38 categories of surveys using ODK and KoBo Toolbox, monitored the progress of ongoing activities, and assessed the impact of the project intervention. I analyzed data for reports

using Excel, SPSS, ArcGIS, and suitable tools for the specific type of data. I also prepared 4 monitoring guidelines and 3 working manuals for field staff. I also provided information to the management and implementation team to make decisions and mitigation the situation and contributed to knowledge management and monitoring system. The remarkable study I have done in this period are — installing 150 managed aquifer recharge (MAR) and rainwater harvesting (RWH) systems, installing 08 Rugged TROLL 100 and Rugged BaroTROLL Data Loggers, cost-benefit analysis (CBA), water footprint, economic valuation of water, web-based water resources mapping as a management tool and water modelling for empirically identifying water stressed area.

3. March 2013 - July 2014 as 'Research Associate' in the Dept. of Geology and Mining, University of Rajshahi under the supervision of Professor Dr. Quamrul Hasan Mazumder. Engaged in the 3 short term projects- (i) Hydro-geologist Expert for Survey Conduction and Preparation of Hydro-geological Profile to Install Aquifer Recharge Well in Chapai-Nawabganj District. (ii) A Viable Solution to Groundwater Depletion in Barind Area, Northwest of Bangladesh and (iii) Survey Conduction and Preparation of Hydro-geological Profile to Identify and Assess the Potential/Safe Shallow and Deep Aquifer for Mini Pipeline Water Supply in Barodhutpatila, Damurhuda Upazilla, Chuadanga District. I assisted Supervisor in taking 27 Vertical Electrical Sounding (VES) data and monitoring the data collection activities, analyzed the collected data using Excel, SPSS and ArcGIS program and prepared field reports.

PERSONAL SKILLS

Communication skills:

- Mother tongue(s): Bengali
- Foreign Languages: English (Overall IELTS Score 6.00), German (One Year Certificate Course), Hindi (Good at speaking)
- Good communication skills gained through my work of liaison with NGO, govt. department and different stakeholders

Organisational/managerial skills:

- Leadership (currently responsible for supervising a team of 23 people)
- Good in team management (conducted 45 different surveys by the hired and internal enumerator)
- Good in project management (completed 5 projects with consultants)
- Good organizational skills gained as Vice President of Rotaract Club Rajshahi University under Rotary Club Rajshahi and as Organizer of Earth Olympiad of Bangladesh Youth Environmental Initiative (BYEI)

Project Monitored, Supervised, and Achievement

- 52 LGI's Web-based water resources mapping with Map engine and API developed after conducting a survey
- 1272 Community-based Water Resource Management Committee formed, monitored, and supervised
- 60 Groundwater monitoring well monitored regularly and reported the fluctuation
- 8 loggers installed for continuous groundwater monitoring and reported (<u>Report</u>)
- 22 Geoelectric Resistivity Survey conducted at Tanore, Rajshahi (2015), Godagari, Rajshahi (2015), Chuadanga, Jessore (2014), Nachole, Chapai Nawabganj (2013), Rajshahi (2012) and Porsha and Sapahar, Naogaon (2011), Bangladesh

DIGITAL SKILLS

- Multidisciplinary Application of Geographic Information System (GIS)
- Good command in Open Data Kit (ODK), KoBo Toolbox, Tableau, R, Python, SPSS, STATA
- Basic computing with MS Office and FORTRAN language learned through a one-year course curriculum
- Skilled in image processing and graphics with Adobe Photoshop and illustrator, video editing
- Good at Web Designing (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jquery, PHP), Visual Basic, and Java.
- Good command in networking and Intranet, E-Mail Applications, Social Networking, Audio-Visual Conferencing, Instant messaging, online event management.

MEMBERSHIPS

- Member (Membership no: 8369), Groundwater Relief (Charity Number: 1167458), Providing hydrogeological support to humanitarian and development organisations, www.groundwater-relief.org
- Member, Gender and Water Alliance (GWA), Dieren, the Netherlands, Email: secretariat@gwalliance.org
- Member, Gender and Evaluation Community, A part of EvalGender+, EvalPartners.
- Member, Gender and Equity Network South Asia-GENSA. GENSA is a special interest group of the Community of Evaluators – South Asia (COESA). Email: gensanetwork@gmail.com
- Vulunteer, EvalYouth, https://volunteer.evalyouth.org/?page_id=8&um_user=suman
- Member, Rajshahi University Rotaractors Alumni Association (RURAA), Dhaka, Bangladesh.
 Rotaractors are a member of the Rotaract Club and sponsored by Rotary International.
- Member, betterevaluation community, https://www.betterevaluation.org/
- Individual Member, Sharenet International, https://share-netinternational.org/user/suman/

PUBLICATIONS

- Water Footprint and Governance Assessment for Sustainable Water Resource Management in Drought-Prone Barind Area, NW Bangladesh, (2019), https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-01572-5_87
- Rainwater Harvesting to Alleviate Water Scarcity in drought-prone Barind Tract, NW, Bangladesh:
 A Case Study, (2016), Proceeding Published in 1st International Conference on Botanical
 Pesticide and Environmental Sustainability. 24-26, IES, University of Rajshahi, Bangladesh,
 http://www.ru.ac.bd/ies/conference/
- Conference paper: MAR Model with IWRM Approach in Barind Tract: An Adaptation Tool for Alleviating Water Scarcity in Thirsty Hard-to-Reach Area in NW Bangladesh (2021). Abstarct on 7th Gobeshona International Conference_18-24 January, 2021.
- Work paper: Economic Valuation of Small Scale Water Management Intervention in Barind Area, Bangladesh. AIJR Preprints, 250, Version 1, 2020. https://preprints.aijr.org/index.php/ap/preprint/view/250
- Book: Field Data Collection Method using KoBo Toolbox, (2016), DASCOH Foundation, Rajshahi.
- Video Documentary: Women and Water, (2020), Scripted and Supervised.
- Book: Mouza Map Atlas (2017), DASCOH Foundation, Rajshahi.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Information Technology Passport Examination (IP), 2017 passed. by Bangladesh IT-engineers Examination Center (BDITEC), Bangladesh Computer Council, Passer ID #IP2017OCT00041
- Database Programming Certificate in Skill Standard Basic Course Examination 2015, by Bangladesh Technical Education Board, Dhaka; Secured Grade: A+, Reg. No: 857355, SI No: 2250486.
- International English Language Testing System (IELTS), 2020. Overall Score 6.00 with speaking: 6.5
- Certified Online Moderators, November 2020, by Diplo Foundation.

CONFERENCES

- Presented work paper in regional alumni training and conference on Climate Change, Water management & Food security on 20-22 November 2019 in Bangkok, Thailand.
- Presented conference paper on MAR Model with IWRM Approach in Barind Tract: An Adaptation Tool for Alleviating Water Scarcity in Thirsty Hard-to-Reach Area in NW Bangladesh (2021). 7th Gobeshona International Conference_18-24 January, 2021. (Virtual)
- Rainwater Harvesting to Alleviate Water Scarcity in drought-prone Barind Tract, NW, Bangladesh:
 A Case Study, (2016), International Conference on Botanical Pesticide and Environmental
 Sustainability. Institute of Environmental Science, University of Rajshahi, Bangladesh.

REFERENCES

References Available Upon Request

DECLARATION

I, the undersigned, certify to the best of my knowledge and belief that this CV correctly describes myself, my qualifications, and my experience, and I am available, as and when necessary, to undertake the assignment in case of an award. I understand that any misstatement or misrepresentation described herein may lead to my disqualification or dismissal by the Client.

Md. Suman Miah

Owner hinh